<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TEI Lex0</title>
        <author>TEI Lex0 Task Force</author>
        <editor xml:id="PB">Piotr Bański</editor>
        <editor xml:id="JB">Jack Bowers</editor>
        <editor xml:id="ET">Tomaž Erjavec</editor>
        <editor xml:id="LR">Laurent Romary</editor>
        <editor xml:id="TT">Toma Tasovac</editor>
        <editor>Berlin TEI-Lex0 task force, to be named individually as we proceed</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>no official publisher atm</publisher>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Fully compatible with TEI Guidelines licensing: BSD-2 or CC BY-SA 3.0</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Based on TEI Absolutely Bare derived from Roma. See the changelog.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>This is where TEI-Lex0 should be described.</p>
        <p>One bibliographic reference that needs to be made is ISO 24611:2012 Language resource management -- Morpho-syntactic annotation framework (MAF), which supplies names for the grammatical categories.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2017-10-28" who="#PB">Added <gi>encodingDesc</gi> and <gi>projectDesc</gi> because this is probably always useful.</change>
      <change when="2017-10-04" who="#PB">Removed the public domain residue (but made sure to keep a
        trace in this changelog and the full history in the git log, as a tribute to our
        colleagues); given the successful resolution of <ref
          target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1688">ticket #1688</ref>, customization of
          <gi>form</gi> removed (it is now a member of att.typed).</change>
      <change when="2017-09-26" who="#PB">based on TEI Absolutely Bare, with thanks to all the
        co-authors of that customization (full credits and changelog available from Roma, TEI
        sources or the history of this document as preserved by git; thanks go to: Laurent, Lou,
        Sebastian and Syd). TEI Absolutely Bare was initially created on <date
          when="2006-10-12T05:24:41">Thursday 12th October 2006</date> and has been improved over
        time but the above-mentioned lovely and dear individuals. It has been converted from Public
        Domain to the TEI Guidelines licensing scheme on <date when="2017-09-26T20:45:11">Tuesday
          26th September 2017</date>.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <!--    <front>
      <divGen type="toc"/>
    </front>-->
    <body>
      <p>This customization expresses the requirements defined within initiative known as TEI Lex0, initiated in December 2016 in Berlin by a group of concerned individuals gathered together by the magnetic power of Laurent Romary and Toma Tasovac. More historical and technical details will surely follow at some point.</p>
      <p>The text below shall be adjusted in due time. There is nothing normative about it, for now (as of September 2017).</p>

      <div>
        <head>Purpose</head>
        <p>To be added. Note that this customisation has been created as an extension of the work of the group focusing on the encoding of forms. It is expected and hoped that the other groups of the TEI Lex0 Task Force will join in.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Initial Changes</head>
        <p>The Dictionaries module has been imported without some of the legacy structure-building elements, such as <gi>entryFree</gi>, <gi>hom</gi> or <gi>superEntry</gi>. The named children of <gi>gramGrp</gi> are absent as well, except for <gi>gram</gi> with the obligatory <att>type</att> attribute.</p>
        <p><gi>subc</gi> (?) and <gi>colloc</gi> are likewise missing, and will be replaced by <gi>gram</gi> (?) and <gi>cit</gi>, respectively</p>
        <p>We need some Schematron here to implement the decisions of the Task Force.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Basic text structure</head>
        <p>In this very simple schema, a document may contain <gi>front</gi>, <gi>body</gi> and
            <gi>back</gi> elements as in standard TEI. However, within these, only the following
          elements are permitted: <specList>
            <specDesc key="div"/>
            <specDesc key="head"/>
            <specDesc key="list"/>
            <specDesc key="p"/>
          </specList>
        </p>
        <p>The <gi>list</gi> element may contain a <gi>head</gi> followed by a sequence either of
            <gi>label</gi>-<gi>item</gi> pairs, or of <gi>item</gi> elements alone. </p>
        <p>The <gi>item</gi> and <gi>p</gi> elements have the same structure: either may contain
          just text, or a mixture of text with <gi>list</gi>, or <gi>title</gi> elements.</p>
        <p>Similarly, the <gi>div</gi> element may contain a <gi>head</gi>, followed by a nested
            <gi>div</gi>, or one or more <gi>p</gi> elements. </p>
        <p>The <att>version</att> attribute on the <gi>TEI</gi> element is removed, as is the
            <att>level</att> attribute on the <gi>title</gi> element. Other attributes are also
          removed as a consequence of the class modifications described below.</p>
        <p>The following specification group deletes the unwanted attributes: <specGrp
            xml:id="bodyfixes">
            <elementSpec ident="title" mode="change" module="core">
              <attList>
                <attDef ident="level" mode="delete"/>
              </attList>
            </elementSpec>
            <elementSpec ident="TEI" mode="change" module="textstructure">
              <attList>
                <attDef ident="version" mode="delete"/>
              </attList>
            </elementSpec>
          </specGrp>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Header structure</head>
        <p>A much simplified version of the TEI Header is defined, again by the deletion of many
          elements. For validity, all that is required within it is the <gi>fileDesc</gi>, which
          contains only the following elements: <specList>
            <specDesc key="titleStmt"/>
            <specDesc key="publicationStmt"/>
            <specDesc key="sourceDesc"/>
          </specList>
        </p>
        <p>Within the <gi>titleStmt</gi> only a <gi>title</gi> is permitted; within the other two
          elements only a <gi>p</gi> is permitted. The <att>default</att> attribute on the
            <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element is also removed. <specGrp xml:id="hdrfixes">
            <elementSpec ident="sourceDesc" mode="change" module="header">
              <attList>
                <attDef ident="default" mode="delete"/>
              </attList>
            </elementSpec>
          </specGrp>
        </p>
        <p>TEI-Lex0 adds <gi>encodingDesc</gi> as well, for the purpuse of describing the given project.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Class modifications</head>
        <p>Finally three of the TEI attribute classes are simplified. The attributes xml:space,
          rend, and xml:base are removed from the att.global class, so that this now makes available
          to all elements only the following attributes: <att>xml:id</att>, <att>n</att>, and
            <att>xml:lang</att>. </p>
        <p>Three un-needed attributes are removed from the att.divLike class so that the
            <gi>div</gi> element inherits from it only the following attributes: <att>xml:id</att>,
            <att>n</att>, <att>xml:lang</att>. The attribute class <ident>att.declaring</ident> is
          deleted completely, so that none of its members inherit the <att>decls</att> attribute
          defined in the unmodified TEI.</p>
        <specGrp xml:id="classmods">
          <classSpec ident="att.global" mode="change" module="tei" type="atts">
            <attList>
              <attDef ident="xml:space" mode="delete"/>
              <attDef ident="rend" mode="delete"/>
              <attDef ident="xml:base" mode="delete"/>
            </attList>
          </classSpec>
          <classSpec ident="att.fragmentable" mode="delete" module="tei" type="atts"/>
          <classSpec ident="att.divLike" mode="change" module="tei" type="atts">
            <attList>
              <attDef ident="org" mode="delete"/>
              <attDef ident="sample" mode="delete"/>
            </attList>
          </classSpec>
          <classSpec ident="att.declaring" mode="delete" module="tei" type="atts"/>
        </specGrp>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Formal declaration</head>
        <schemaSpec ident="Lex0" xml:lang="en">
          <moduleRef key="core" include="p list item label head author title"/>
          <moduleRef key="tei"/>
          <moduleRef key="header" include="teiHeader fileDesc titleStmt publicationStmt sourceDesc encodingDesc projectDesc"/>
          <moduleRef key="textstructure" include="TEI text body div front back"/>
          <specGrpRef target="#classmods"/>
          <specGrpRef target="#bodyfixes"/>
          <specGrpRef target="#hdrfixes"/>
          
          <!-- TEI Lex0 section begins here -->
          <moduleRef key="dictionaries" except="case colloc entryFree gen hom hyph iType mood number per pos subc superEntry tns"/>
          <!-- Schematron needed for various constraints -->

          <moduleRef key="linking" include="seg" /> <!-- for segmentation inside orth/pron -->

          <moduleRef key="namesdates" include="placeName"/> <!-- for dialectal properties -->

<!-- the modification of <form> will not be needed after the next version of the Guidelines is published (as of Oct. 2017)  -->
          <elementSpec ident="form" mode="change" module="dictionaries">
            <!-- enable @subtype -->
            <constraintSpec scheme="schematron" ident="subtypeTyped" mode="add">
              <constraint>
                <sch:rule context="tei:*[@subtype]" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron">
                  <sch:assert test="@type">The <sch:name/> element should not be categorized in
                    detail with @subtype unless also categorized in general with @type</sch:assert>
                </sch:rule>
              </constraint>
            </constraintSpec>
            <attList>
              <attDef ident="subtype" usage="opt" mode="add">
                <desc versionDate="2005-10-10" xml:lang="en">provides a sub-categorization of the
                  element, if needed</desc>
                <datatype>
                  <dataRef key="teidata.enumerated"/>
                </datatype>
                <remarks versionDate="2013-01-13" xml:lang="en">
                  <p>The <att>subtype</att> attribute may be used to provide any sub-classification
                    for the element additional to that provided by its <att>type</att>
                    attribute.</p>
                </remarks>
              </attDef>
            </attList>
          </elementSpec>

          <elementSpec ident="orth" mode="change" module="dictionaries">
            <classes mode="change">
              <memberOf key="att.datable.w3c" mode="add"/> 
              <memberOf key="att.notated" mode="add"/>
            </classes>
          </elementSpec>

        </schemaSpec>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>

